主啊 我要赞颂你的圣名
I will give glory to thee O Lord: for you have saved me.
拯救我于不公 毁谤与不公的国王
from injustice, from slanderous tongues and an unjust king.
我将始终颂赞你 直至生命最后一刻
My soul shall praise thee even to the last to my death,
因为你救赎那些等待您降临的人
for thou deliveries those that wait for thee.
够了
ENOUGH!
恭迎公主殿下
Make way for Princess Elizabeth.
为公主让路
Make way there.
让开道路
Make way for her Grace.
- 金斯顿大人 - 夫人
- Master Kingston. - My Lady.
夫人 我现在向您宣布国王的裁决
My Lady, I can now tell you that the King has decreed.
您将被处以斩首之刑
that you will not be burned,
免受火刑之苦
but suffer a quicker death by decapitation.
陛下仁慈 恩准了您的请求
In his mercy, the King has also acceded to your plea.
交由加来的刽子手执行斩首
to use the services of the Executioner of Calais,
目前他正从多佛赶来
who is even now on his way here from Dover.
- 何时执行 - 上午九时
- When am I to die? - At nine o'clock.
我别无他求了
I am content.
可否请克朗默大主教前来
Will you please send for Archbishop Cranmer,
聆听我的临终忏悔 施行临终圣体
so he may hear my last confession and administer Holy Communion?
遵命 夫人
My Lady.
皇帝贤侄收鉴
"To the Emperor. Nephew.
想必此消息
"This day will bring you, I think,
甚合君意
"news of great satisfaction.
你我二人当冰释前嫌
"Let us put all quarrels behind us.
共同促进两国间贸易
"And work for an accommodation that will increase the trade.
共同繁荣
"and prosperity between us.
结盟对抗法王鼠辈
"And unite us against that bastard, the King of France.
我对变化所带来的希望尤为喜悦
"Above all, I love the prospect of change."
金斯顿大人 夫人近况如何
Master Kingston, tell me, how is the Lady?
恕在下直言 在她囚禁初期
Truthfully, in the early days of her captivity.
言语甚为放肆
she often spoke rather wildly.
例如 除非将她释放 否则天将大旱
For example, that it would not rain until she was released.
近来她的施赈吏上报
But now, according to her almoner,
她的赴死之念渐炽
preparations for death have increasingly occupied her thoughts,
因此我认为她将甘心受刑
and so I believe she is reconciled to it.
我甚感欣慰
I am glad.
然而
Although…
我却不得不加重她的痛苦
it grieves me that I must cause her further pain.
夫人 我不得已相告
My Lady, I am obliged to tell you.
您与国王的婚姻已经被宣布无效
that your marriage to the King has been declared null and void.
什么理由
On what grounds?
基于发现您的至亲左近曾与国王
On the grounds of your close and forbidden degree of affinity.
发生肌肤之亲
to another woman known carnally by the King.
我妹妹…
My sister…
- 那么我女儿是… ？- 是的
- Then my daughter is…? - Yes.
伊丽莎白将被宣布为私生子
Elizabeth is to be declared a bastard.
夫人 我向你发誓 我将倾尽全力
Madam, I swear to you I will do everything within my power.
保护和拥护她 留住国王对她的
to protect and support her, and keep her always.
仁慈与怜爱
in the King's good and kind graces.
谢谢
Thank you.
我的大限将至
And now, since my time approaches,
我恳请主教大人聆听我的忏悔
I beg your Grace to hear my confession.
同时 我希望在接受主时
Also, I should like the Constable present.
警役可以在场
when I receive the good Lord.
遵命 夫人
Madam.
我的孩子 你有忏悔之意吗
My child, do you have a confession?
是的
Yes.
我在上帝面前发誓 我是清白的
I confess my innocence before God.
我庄严发誓 以我的灵魂起誓
I solemnly swear, on the damnation of my soul,
我从未对我夫君不忠
that I have never been unfaithful to my lord and husband,
亦从未有过任何肉体背叛行为
nor ever offended with my body against him.
我并非说我一直
I do not say that I have always borne towards him.
对他谦卑贤淑
the humility which I owed him,
鉴于他的仁慈 赐予我的荣光
considering his kindness and the great honor he showed me.
以及给予我莫大的尊重
and the great respect he always paid me.
我承认自己时常对他
I admit, too, that I have often taken it into my head.
心存妒嫉
to be jealous of him.
但此心可鉴 上帝作证
But God knows, and is my witness,
我再无任何其他方式违犯于他
I have not sinned against him in any other way.
切勿以为我这样说是为了苟活
Think not I say this in the hope to prolong my life.
上帝已教会我如何面对死亡 坚定我的信仰
God has taught me how to die, and He will strengthen my faith.
至于我弟弟
As for my brother…
以及那些受到不公正的罪罚的人
and those others who were unjustly condemned,
我甘领数死以拯救他们
I would willingly have suffered many deaths to deliver them,
既然陛下乐于如此
but since I see it pleases the King,
我便甘愿与他们一同赴死
I will willingly accompany them in death.
我确信
With this assurance…
我将与他们一起获得安宁之永生
that I shall lead an endless life with them in peace.
以圣父 圣子 圣灵的名义
In the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
金斯顿大人
Master Kingston.
请务必记录下夫人诚恳的临终忏悔
Please go and make sure to report my Lady's true and last confession,
以便世人了解
so the world will know it.
我会的
I will.
克朗默阁下
Mr. Cranmer,
即使是最后的时刻 我也未曾想过
I do not suppose that, even at this last hour,
让福音派的主教替我斡旋
the evangelical bishops that we put in place might intervene for me?
陛下 我…
Your Majesty, I…
不 我明白
No, I understand.
他们怎么会呢？请见谅
How could they? Forgive me.
你们要靠主常常喜乐 永永远远 阿门
Gaudeamus omnes in Domino, per omnia saecula saeculorum. Amen.
结束了吗 那个人尽可夫的女人死了？
Is it done? Is the harlot dead?
不甚了解 但她离死期不远矣
I don't know. But, certainly, she will be dead before very long.
苍天有眼
The Lord is good.
跟我说说她被判死刑的原因
Tell me: why is she really to die?
据说她的女儿 伊丽莎白
They say that her child, Elizabeth,
并非国王的骨肉
was not conceived with the King at all,
而是与她其中一个情人所生
but with one of her countless lovers.
她大概有多少情人
How many lovers was she supposed to have?
据克伦威尔阁下声称 有一百余人
According to Mr. Cromwell, over a hundred men,
其中包括她弟弟 洛克福特
including her brother, Rochford.
听闻她将自己所遭受的厄运全都归咎于我
But I'm told she also blames me for what has befallen her,
指责我对此负有不可推卸的责任
and holds me accountable for her doom.
我自然是对这种「恭维」感到「欣喜」
Naturally I am flattered by the compliment,
因为她早想把我喂狗了
since she would have thrown me to the dogs if she could.
那位珍·西摩女士如何
Tell me about this other Lady, this Jane Seymour?
有密报说她支持我们
I have been told in confidence that she is of our faith,
国王爱她 欲娶她为妻
and that the King loves her, and means to marry her.
而且她有意谏言恢复殿下的继承权
And that she means to restore your grace to the succession.
伊丽莎白如今也成了私生子？
And Elizabeth will become a bastard now?
正如当年宣布我为私生子一样
As I have been a bastard?
是的 公主
Yes, Princess.
现已正式宣布这个乳臭未干的小孩为私生子
The brat is now officially a bastard.
命人备马
Tell them to ready the horses.
但去向保密
But tell no one of our destination.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Majesty.
凡事皆有定期
To every thing there is a season,
天下万务皆有定时
and a time to every purpose under heaven.
生有时 死有时
A time to be born, and a time to die.
栽种有时 拔出所栽种的 也有时
A time to plant and a time to pluck up that which is planted.
哭有时
A time to weep,
笑有时
and a time to laugh.
抛掷石头有时
A time to cast away stones,
堆聚石头有时
and a time to gather stones together.
哀恸有时 跳舞有时
A time to mourn, and a time to dance.
现今的事早先就有了
That which hath been is now.
经来的事也早已有了
And that which is to be has already been…
寻梢有时 失落有时
A time to get, and a time to lose.
保守有时 舍弃有时
A time to keep, and a time to cast away.
撕裂有时 缝补有时
A time to rend, and a time to sew.
静默有时 言语有时
A time to keep silence, and a time to speak.
我心里说 神必审判义人和恶人
I said in my heart, God shall judge the righteous and the wicked,
因为在那里 天下万务皆有定时
for there is a time for every purpose under the sun.
我现在就要出发吗 我还以为…
Am I to go now? I thought…
请原谅 夫人
My Lady, forgive me…
从多佛来的刽子手在路上耽搁了
The executioner has been delayed on the road from Dover.
所以您的行刑将延时至十二点
and your execution is postponed until twelve o'clock.
我想及时告诉你 以防万一…
I wanted to tell you, in good time, in case…
金斯顿大人
Master Kingston.
您是说正午之前我都不会死了
I hear you say I will not die before noon,
真是遗憾
and I'm sorry for it,
我以为那时候我就死了 解脱痛苦了
for I thought to be dead by that time, and past my pain.
夫人 不会疼的
Madam, there will be no pain.
几乎感觉不到挥剑而下
The blow will be so subtle.
是啊 听说那个刽子手技法精湛
Yes, I heard the executioner was very good.
不管怎么说 我的脖子很细
And in any case, I have only a little neck.
爱德华
Edward!
父亲？
Father?
大人？
Sir?
我的上帝
My God.
爱德华 这可不是玩具
Edward, this is not a toy.
是的 大人
Yes, sir.
那么 您杀过人吗
So, have you ever killed someone?
有 在战场上
Yes. In battle.
那是什么样的感觉？
What did it feel like?
他是我的敌人
He was my enemy.
我根本不在乎
I didn't care.
我很想看看人死的样子
I would really like to see someone die.
我能和您一起去刑场吗
Can I go to the execution with you?
那个断头台他们要价多少？
How much did they charge for the scaffold?
23英磅6先令8便士 大臣阁下
Twenty-three pounds, six shillings and eight pence, Mr. Secretary.
光天化日下抢劫
Daylight robbery.
如果那个刽子手能赶到的话 要付他多少？
And what is the Headsman to be paid, if he ever arrives?
15英镑
Fifteen pounds.
15英镑？
Fifteen pounds?
就那么一刀？
For one stroke?
我的天 他的活可太好赚了
My God, he makes a damn good living!
走吧 继续往前
Allons, vas-y. Allons-y.
到那里去 快
On y va. Viens!
已经斩首了？
Well, is it done?
结束了？
Is it?
没有陛下 非常不幸
No, your Majesty. Uh… Unfortunately,
我们又要延迟行刑了
we must postpone the execution again.
- 什么？- 刽子手还没到
- What? - The Executioner was delayed.
那就再找一个 听见了没？
Then you fetch somebody else! Do you hear?
把那个给其他人行刑的刽子手找回来
Fetch back the axman who did the others!
他够好了吧？没搞砸过事
He was good enough wasn't he? He didn't botch the thing.
可陛下您承诺过
Your Majesty made a promise.
我为什么要遵守对那个妓女的承诺？
Why should I care about my promises to that whore?!
您的承诺业已昭告天下 那是…
Your Majesty's promise is public knowledge. That is all…
我不在乎
I still don't care!
我命令你另找一人 我要她死
I ordered you to get someone else! I want her dead!
我想结束这一切
I want it over with! Finished!
如果不想和她一样 就照我说的做
Go and do it or by God's blood you will join her!
我下令
I said!
延时执行
Postpone it!
遵命 陛下
Majesty.
我们走
Let's go.
金斯顿大人 我准备好了
Master Kingston, I am ready.
夫人 我再次请求您的宽恕
My Lady, you must forgive me once again.
刽子手仍未到达
But the Executioner is still not arrived.
你说什么？
What do you say?
夫人 您的行刑将改在明日上午九时
Madam, your execution is put off until nine o'clock tomorrow morning.
不…
No…
不 这不是真的
No. It cannot be.
不是说我想死 只是我…
It is not that I desire death, but I…
我做好了赴死的准备 我准备好了
I thought myself prepared to die… I was prepared.
我怕…
I fear…
我怕一再的延迟会动摇我的决心
I fear that of further delay it may weaken my resolve.
求求你 如果… 如果可能的话
Please… If it… If it were possible…
不行 夫人 这是国王陛下的命令
No, Madam. It is the King's express command.
等等 可能这意味着我命不该绝
No! Wait! Perhaps I'm not meant to die.
一再改期一定意味着什么
These postponements they mean something.
可能国王陛下是在试探我
Perhaps the King is testing me.
我会被送到女修道院
I'll be sent to a nunnery.
驾
Hiya!
约翰爵士 想必你已得知
I am sure you are aware, Sir John,
我的婚姻已被宣布无效
that my marriage has been declared null and void.
我已有所耳闻 陛下
I have been made aware of the circumstances, your Majesty.
如其他人一样
And, like everyone else, I have been shocked.
我对此也感到十分震惊
and utterly amazed by what I've heard.
多劳挂怀 但我必须要说
I am grateful. But I must tell you…
尽管已屡次受到伤害
The Privy Council, despite these recent hurts,
枢密院恳请我再尝试一次婚姻
have pleaded with me to venture once more into matrimony,
并希望新娘能为我诞下合法的继承人
in the hope that my bride will produce a legitimate heir.
想必您也知道我选择了令嫒
I think you know my choice has fallen upon your daughter.
是的
I do.
明日你们将乘游船前往汉普顿宫
Tomorrow you will all travel by barge to Hampton Court,
我们将在那儿宣布订婚
where our betrothal will be announced.
我向您发誓 约翰爵士
I swear to you, Sir John,
从明天起 一切将焕然一新
from tomorrow, everything will be different.
我们将如往昔般充满活力 神怿气愉
We will be young and merry as we used to be.
- 敬珍女士 - 陛下
- Lady Jane. - Your Majesty.
敬珍女士
Lady Jane!
我不想穿 你不能强迫我
I won't wear it! You can't make me!
不要不要 我不走
No! No! I'm not going!
伊丽莎白小姐 你必须照做
Lady Elizabeth, you must do as you are told!
安静 否则我要打你了
Now hush! Or I will hit you.
别这样看我 孩子
Don't look like that, girl!
我们奉命将孩子
We are ordered to remove the child.
转移到国王视线以外
so she can be kept out of sight of the King.
- 小公主 - 她已经不是公主了
- Little Princess. - She is no longer a Princess.
而是私生子
She is a bastard.
克伦威尔大人还要求把她的账目理清
And Master Cromwell has asked for her accounts to be settled.
包括为她母亲在伦敦塔中提供的必需品
Also in respect of necessities provided for her mother in the Tower.
你是说 要她承担她母亲关押时的费用
You mean, the child should pay for her mother's imprisonment?
是的 从国王提供的生活费中扣除
Yes. Out of the money the King pays for her household.
就是这样
Exactly.
这是个复杂多变的世界 女士
The world is a slippery place, my Lady.
如果你肯听我一言
If you would take my advice, for what it's worth,
找个有钱人嫁了吧
find a rich man to marry.
还要是个对政治一窍不通的笨蛋
who is too stupid to know anything about politics.
之后除非你死于难产 有这个可能
Then, perhaps, unless you die in childbirth, which is likely,
或是在不可避免的瘟疫中丧生
or the plague, which is almost inevitable…
那么你将会很幸福
then you will be happy.
你想聊些什么呢 亲爱的
What would you like to talk about, sweetheart?
如果陛下不介意的话
If your Majesty would allow,
我想谈谈您的女儿玛丽
I should like to talk about your daughter Mary.
我希望我当王后时
When I am Queen.
能看到她重获继承权
I would hope to see her reinstated as heir apparent.
珍 就你这个小傻瓜才会这么想
Jane, you're a fool to hope so.
你应该为我们将来的孩子
You ought to solicit the advancement.
恳求这个权力 而不是其他人的孩子
of the children we're going to have, not any others.
但是陛下 我这么做不是为
But, Your Majesty, I thought I was asking not so much.
别人求好 而是为您的心境
for the good of others, as for the good of the repose.
安详宁静着想
and tranquility of yourself,
也为我们未来的孩子
as well as the children we may have ourselves.
以及陛下的王国太平
And for the tranquility of your Majesty's kingdom.
原谅我
Forgive me.
我只是太想要一个崭新的开始
It's just that I so much want a new beginning.
一场复兴
A renaissance.
有时往事不堪提 你理解吗？
Sometimes it is hard to be reminded of things. Do you understand?
你是如此纯洁
You are so pure.
我只是不想让你被陈年往事困扰
I just don't want you to be affected by things that have gone before.
我可以吻你吗 珍？
May I kiss you, Jane?
你不是英格兰国王吗？
Aren't you the King of England?
一切将为她而改变
Everything will change for her.
那吻是她的命运与财富
That kiss is her destiny, and her fortune.
我们亦然
And ours.
在我还是小女孩时 我在奥地利的玛格丽特宫廷当差
You know, when I was a girl, I served at the court of Margaret of Austria.
曾是多么美妙的时光
It was a wonderful time.
壮丽的场面和舞会
Pageants and dances.
很多很多的舞会
So many dances.
有次我曾经扮作亚马逊人的女王
I once appeared as the Queen of the Amazons,
手里舞着剑
with a naked sword in my hand,
戴着绯红的头饰和巨大的羽毛
and a crimson headdress with a great plume!
玛格丽特也同样聪颖智慧
But Margaret was wise, too.
她告诫我们：「要信任那些服侍你的人
She said to us: "Trust in those who offer you service,
「少女们 因为你们将发现
"and in the end, my maidens, you will find yourself in the ranks.
最终会被那些头衔显赫的人所欺骗「
of those who have been deceived."
是不是
Am I…
我将被审讯？
Am I to be tried?
不 你将被释放
No. You are to be released.
但是 陛下谕令如下
But, his Majesty commands,
鉴于你不再受宠信
that since you no longer enjoy his trust or affection,
将立即褫夺
you are to be stripped forthwith.
你所有的官职与头衔
of all your official posts and titles.
你将不再任职于枢密院
You will no longer serve on the Privy Council,
不再担任掌玺大臣一职
you will relinquish the role of Lord Privy Seal,
及其所有特权
and all its privileges.
陛下也要求你立即离宫
His Majesty also desires that you leave court.
永远离开陛下的视线
And that you never show yourself in his presence again.
违者以死论处
On pain of death.
这么说我将保留我的伯爵身份？
So I am to keep my earldom?
你是否看过你儿子被处死？
Did you watch your son die?
你的女儿又如何？
What about your daughter?
你是否会看她受刑？
Will you watch her suffer?
你是否会看她受死？
Will you watch her die?
告诉我 波林 这一切值得吗？
Tell me, Boleyn: was it all worth it?
停
Halt!
看见了吗？
Do see this?
知道这是什么吗？
Do you know what this is?
这是青春之泉
It's the Fountain of Youth.
看吧
Look!
我已获重生
I am re-born!
这边请 先生
This way, Monsieur.
很抱歉有所耽搁
I deeply regret you were delayed.
可否观赏一下？
May I see it?
请随意 先生
Si vous voulez, Monsieur.
很漂亮 对吗？
It's beautiful, no?
行刑时间为九时
The execution is ordered for nine o'clock.
您将在二个小时前被叫醒 以便您能食用早餐
You will be awoken two hours before, in order for you to have breakfast.
- 此外还有别的事情吗？- 是的 先生
- So, if that is all? - No, Monsieur.
我有几句话要说
I must say a few words.
夫人绝对不能带任何镣铐
The lady must not to be restrained in any way.
而且 对夫人非常重要的是
But, it is very important that the lady.
不能回头观看从而会对此剑产生恐惧
doesn't look back like this for the fear of the sword.
所以首先 我会把剑掩藏到她看不见的地方
Alors first, I hide the sword so she cannot see it.
通常他们都会四处观望
It is totally normal they want to look around.
想看看死亡来自何方 对吧？
and see where your death come from. No? Ha! Ha!
因此 当她完成祷告准备赴死时
So, when she has finished her prayers, and is ready to go…
我会对在她前面男孩说「取我的剑来」
I say, to boy in front of her, "Fetch my sword".
当然夫人会注视那人
Of course the lady looks at man.
这便是对我最完美的角度
And this is just the perfect angle for me.
在她注视那人时 我便猛然挥剑
When she looks at man. Then I strike.
然后「喀嚓」
Then, "Chuck!"
您明白了吗？
You understand?
是的 我明白了
I think so, yes.
非常快 她不会感觉任何痛苦
Oh, it's very quick. She feel no pain.
先生？
Monsieur?
您将不会失望的
You will be not disappointed.
我确信
I'm sure.
您知无论我是否该当一死
Thou knowest whether I deserve this death.
不要成就我的意思 只要成就你的意思
Not my will O Lord, but thine be done.
我将赞美上主的名号
I will give glory to thy name,
因你赐我帮助与庇护
for thou art my help and my protection.
你已庇护我 保护我
Thou hast protected me and preserved me…
安妮
Anne!
他会找到你
He'll get you!
夫人 时辰已到 请务必备妥
Madam, the hour approaches, you must make ready.
不必过虑您的职责
Acquit yourself of your charge,
我早已备妥
for I have been long prepared.
国王请您带着这个钱包
The King asks that you take this purse.
里面有二十镑
It has twenty pounds in it,
用来支付刽子手的服务
to pay the headsman for his services.
以及布施贫寒
and distribute alms to the poor.
谢谢
Thank you.
请您与您的侍女们随我来
Will you and your ladies follow me.
金斯顿大人 我请求您直到我
Master Kingston, I pray you not to give the signal.
把心中的话讲完 再发行刑信号
for my death until I have spoken what I have the mind to speak.
遵命 夫人
Madam.
虔诚的信徒子民
Good Christian people,
我依法来此受死
I have come here to die, according to the law,
来服从吾王 我的夫君的意志
and thus yield myself to the will of the King, my lord.
国王万岁
Long live the King!
如果在有生之年有触犯龙颜之处
And if, in my life, I ever did offend the King's Grace,
那么我现以一死来偿还
then surely with my death I do now atone…
我祈祷并且祈求所有人
I pray and beseech you all,
为吾王祈祷
to pray for the life of the King.
天佑吾王
God save the King!
我与你们至高无上的君主
My sovereign lord and yours,
乃芸芸众生中之最佳王公
who is one of the best princes on the face of the earth,
他总是待我慈善有加
who has always treated me so well,
因此我衷心赴死
wherefore I submit to death with a good will,
并谦卑请求所有世人宽恕
humbly asking pardon of all the world.
如有人谈论我的事宜
If anyone should take up my case,
我谨请求他们只以善意来评判
I ask them only to judge it kindly.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you… Thank you.
夫人 原谅我必须如此
Madame, forgive me for what I must do.
乐意之极
Gladly.
这只是给你的报酬
And here is your purse.
因此我将辞别世间
Thus I take my leave of the world,
- 辞别你们 - 保佑您…
- and of you. - Bless you…
并且我热诚渴望你们为我祈祷
And I heartily desire you all to pray for me.
求主怜悯您
Lord have mercy on you.
主是我的牧者 我必不至缺乏
The Lord is my shepherd. I shall not be in want.
他使我躺卧在青草地上
He makes me lie down in green pastures.
领我在可安歇的水边
He leads me beside quiet waters…
耶稣 接受我的灵魂
Jesus, receive my soul.
主 怜悯我的灵魂
O Lord God, have pity on my soul.
把我的灵魂托付给基督
To Christ I commend my soul.
耶稣基督接受我的灵魂 主 怜悯我的灵魂
Jesus Christ receive my soul! O Lord God have pity on my soul.
耶稣 接受我的灵魂
Jesus receive my soul.
主 怜悯我的灵魂 耶稣基督
O God have pity on my soul, Jesus Christ.
主 怜悯我的灵魂
O Lord God have pity on my soul.
耶稣 接受我的灵魂
Jesus Christ receive my soul.
谢谢
Thank you.
耶稣 接受我的灵魂 耶稣基督接受我的灵魂
Christ receive my soul. Jesus Christ receive my soul.
主 怜悯我的灵魂
O Lord God have pity on my soul.
把我的灵魂托付给基督
To Christ I commend myself.
耶稣 接受我的灵魂 主 怜悯我的灵魂
Jesus receive my soul. O Lord God have pity on my soul.
把我的灵魂托付给基督
To Christ I commend myself.
少年 拿我的剑来
Boy! Fetch my sword!
为国王御用让路
Make way for the King's household.
让路
Make way.
为国王御用让路
Make way for the King's household.
祝愿主耶稣赐予饮食
May the Lord Jesus be drink and food.